Finding Aid for West Michigan Environmental Action Council Records, 1968-2005
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Educational files
  - Solid Wastes Committee
    - Michigan counties
      - Kent county
        - Plainfield Township Landfill
          - Public Hearing (Box 8)
          - Sanitary Landfill proposal (Box 8)
          - Statements (Box 8)
        - Wyoming City (Box 8)
      - Macomb County-Chesterfield Twp. (Box 9)
      - Montcalm. County-Pierson Twp. (Box 9)
      - Muskegon County
        - Hooker Chemical Co. (Box 9)
        - Story Chemical Co. (Box 9)
        - White Lake 1979 (Box 9)
      - Oakland County-Clinton River (Box 9)
      - Ottawa County-Fenske Landfill (Box 9)
    - Office Paper Recycling (Box 9)
    - Oil Recycling center (Box 9)
    - Sewage Treatment-Muskegon and Holland 1971 (Box 9)
    - Solid Waste Recycling 1971-1972 (Box 9)
    - Toxic Wastes 1971 (Box 9)
    - Waste Management and Treatment
      - Office of Solid Waste (Box 9)
      - Sewage Treatment (Box 9)
    - Other Organizations (Correspondence and reports)
      - EPA
        - Federal Grant Application, 2 folders (Box 9)
        - Model Scope of Work for Resource Recovery (Box 9)
        - Region 8 and 14 Pedco Urban Policies Team (Box 9)
        - President's Urban Policy Program-Source Separation (Box 9)
      - Michigan Coalition for Better Waste Management
        - Committee Histories (Box 9)
        - Conference-Ending Solid Wastefulness-Gull Lake 1978 (Box 9)
        - County Reports
          - Oakland County (Box 9)
          - Oceana County-Pentwater (Box 9)
          - St. Clair County-Fort Gratiot (Box 9)
        - Grant Proposal-Public Involvement (Box 9)
        - Guide to Solid Waste Decision Making in Michigan (Box 9)
        - Waste Management Proposals (Box 9)
        - Background Information (Box 9)
        - Correspondence (Box 9)
      - Recycle Unlimited
        - Board of Directors (Box 9)
        - Department of Public Works (Box 9)
        - Estimated Solid Waste Stream (Box 9)
        - Feasibility Study in Recovering and Recycling (Box 9)
        - Source Separation (Box 9)
        - Statistics 1978-1980 (Box 9)
      - Statewide Coalition for Better Waste Management (Box 9)
      - West Michigan Regional Planning Commission-WMRPC
        - Kent/Ottawa County 1980 (Box 9)
        - Land Use Plan-Region 8 1978 (Box 10)
        - Regionotes November 1980 (Box 10)
        - Ten Ech-Resource Recovery Project 1979-1980 (Box 10)
      - West Michigan Shoreline Regional Development Commission (Box 10)
  - Housing and Zoning Committee
    - Urban Housing-Homesteading
      - Committee on Urban Homesteading 1974 (Box 10)
      - Grand Rapids Planning Department (Box 10)
      - Housing Referral Center 1975 (Box 10)
      - Inspection Team (Box 10)
      - Kent County-Housing Coalition (Box 10)
      - Legislation and legal opinions (Box 10)
      - Neighborhood Alliance (Box 10)
      - Reclining (Box 10)
      - Subcommittee's notes (Box 10)
      - Task force (Box 10)
    - City Center Committee
      - Manhattan Project Phase II; East Grand Rapids (Box 10)
      - Nature Area Development Plan (Box 10)
      - Grand Rapids Riverbank Committee (Box 10)
      - Grand Rapids Riverfront (Box 10)
      - Grand River Banks (Box 10)
    - Air Pollution Committee (Box 10)
  - Legislative Committee
    - Alaska Lands Bill (Box 10)
    - Billboards Bill (Box 10)
    - Bottle Bill
      - Campaign Committee (Box 10)
      - Campaign-Kent Co. (Box 10)
      - Correspondence (Box 10)
      - Reports (Box 10)
    - Community Development Act 1974 (Box 10)
    - Correspondence to Legislature (Box 10)
    - DNR-Gill Nets (Box 10)
    - Federal Legislation (Box 10)
    - Legislative Committee 1974 (Box 10)
    - Mining-Mineral Leasing Activity (Box 11)
    - Mining-Sand Dunes (Box 11)
    - Pigeon River
      - Compromise April 1980-1981 (Box 11)
      - Correspondence 1976-1978 (Box 11)
      - Correspondence 1979-1980 (Box 11)
      - History of Pigeon River Controversy (Box 11)
      - Map (Box 11)
      - Pigeon River Country Advisory Council (Box 11)
      - Report-"Pigeon River How Much Oil?" (Box 11)
    - Porcupine Mountains (Box 11)
    - Tree Removal (Box 11)
    - Trout and Salmon Fund (Box 11)
    - Voting records of Legislators (Box 11)
  - Land Use Committee
    - Correspondence 1973-1974 (Box 11)
    - Environmental History-Laws and Impact Statements (Box 11)
    - Forest Legislation (Box 11)
    - Landscape (Box 11)
    - Law Issues (Box 11)
    - Michigan DNR and Land Use (Box 11)
    - Planning, Viewpoints,-Alternatives, and Options (Box 11)
    - Potential Legislation (Box 11)
    - Public Lands Management (Box 11)
    - Regional Framework Plan (Box 11)
    - Reports and papers (Box 11)
    - Soil Erosion (Box 11)
    - Tax Considerations (Box 11)
    - Zoning (Box 11)
  - Energy Committee-Nuclear Power Files
    - Big Rock Nuclear Plant (Box 11)
    - Consumers Power
      - Peak Load Precinct Documents (Box 11)
      - Rate Increase and Advertising (Box 11)
      - Shareholders Proposal (Box 12)
      - Ten Year Plan (Box 12)
    - Correspondence (Box 12)
    - Donald C. Cook Nuclear Plant (Box 12)
    - Nuclear Advertising (Box 12)
    - Nuclear Conference (Box 12)
    - Nuclear Legislation (Box 12)
    - Nuclear Moratorium (Box 12)
  - Pesticides Committee
    - Gypsy Moths (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 12)
  - Water Committee
    - DNR
      - Dams and the DNR (Box 12)
      - Dam Study Fund (Box 12)
      - Inland Lakes and Streams (Box 12)
      - Maple River Project (Box 12)
      - Soil Conservation Service, Future Projects (Box 12)
    - Grand Rapids Watershed council (Box 12)
    - Grand River Basin Plan (Box 12)
    - Michigan Sea Grant Program (Box 12)
    - Michigan Water Quality Standards and Drains (Box 12)
    - Presque Isle River-Fish Ladder (Box 12)
    - Wabasis Lake (Box 12)
    - WMRPC-Report 208 Water Quality, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - West Michigan Sustainable Business Forum (Box 12)
  - Non-committee correspondence and documents
    - Adopt A Stream (Box 12)
    - Biological Surveys -- various streams (Box 12)
    - Flat River (Box 12)
    - Grand Rapids Citizens Watershed Council (Box 12)
    - Grand Rapids Sewer (Box 12)
    - Gunlake Wetlands (Box 12)
    - River Monitoring (Part 2) (Box 13)
      (Part 1 not included in collection)
    - Sand Dunes
      - General, 3 folders (Box 13)
      - Saugatuck (Box 13)
    - Water Programs: Grants (Box 13)
  - Various Committee Correspondences
    - Michigan Student Environmental Coalition (Box 13)
    - Pesticide Work Group (Box 13)
    - Religion, Ecology, and Spirituality, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Various Work Groups
      - Minutes (Box 13)
- Legislative files
  The Legislative Files reveal WMEAC's interaction with the Michigan legislature and the Governor's office. These files begin with the 75th Legislative session (1969-1970) and continue through the 80th Legislative session (1979-1980). Of interest are materials concerning the legislative histories of bills relating to returnable bottles and cans, off-road vehicles, sand dunes and mineral mining, and the management of solid wastes.
  - 75th Legislative Session 1969-1970
    - HB3055 Michigan EPA (Box 13)
  - 76th Legislative Session 1971-1972
    - HB4948 Inland Lakes and Streams, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - PA346 of 1972 Inland Lakes and Streams (Box 13)
  - 77th Legislative Session 1973-1974
    - HB239; SB117 Environmental Education (Box 13)
    - HB4170 Off Road Vehicles (Box 13)
    - HB4244 Land Use (Box 13)
    - HB4926 Bottle Bill (Box 13)
    - HB505 Land Use-State (Box 13)
    - HB6123 Environmental Review Board (Box 13)
    - SB419 Natural Preservation Act (Box 13)
    - SB946 Solid Waste Authority (Box 13)
    - PA116 Land Use (Box 14)
    - Miscellaneous Legislation (Box 14)
  - 78th Legislative Session 1975-1976
    - HB4038 Sand Dune Mining (Box 14)
    - HB4234 Substitute Land Use (Box 14)
    - HB4341 HB4342 HB4343 Solid Waste (Box 14)
    - HB4296 SB233 Bottle Bill (Box 14)
    - HB4729 Off Road Vehicles (Box 14)
    - HB5054 HB5455 SB1003 Mack and Jacobetti Act (Box 14)
    - HB6247 HB6248 HB6249 Solid Waste (Box 14)
    - SB1234 Mobile Homes (Box 14)
    - SB1394 Change in Refuse Laws (Box 14)
    - Miscellaneous Legislation (Box 14)
  - 79th Legislative Session 1977-1978
    - HB4189 Land Use (Box 14)
    - HB4329 Wetlands (Box 14)
    - HB4591 Zoning (Box 14)
    - HB4804 Solid Waste Management (Box 14)
    - HB6314 Solid Waste Management (Box 14)
    - SBG92 Land Resources Planning Act (Box 14)
    - Miscellaneous Legislation (Box 14)
  - 80th Legislative Session 1979-1980
    - HB4006 Hazardous Waste (Box 14)
    - HB6565 Bottle Bill (Box 14)
    - SB1119 Substitute SB1119 Hydrocarbon Development (Box 14)
  - Committees
    - House Study Committee on Waste Disposal 1977 (Box 14)
    - Tom Matthiew Committee on Waste Disposal 1977 (Box 14)
- Litigation files
  The Litigation Files consist of materials concerning legal cases which either involved WMEAC directly or indirectly through the Michigan Environmental Protection Foundation. Court papers documenting the development of several lawsuits involving the WMEAC are complete, and reveal how the WMEAC either defended established statutes against industry and/or government's attempts to interpret these statutes in a manner which could result in potential damage to the environment; or how the WMEAC sued individuals, industry, and government when specific environmental statutes were being ignored or disobeyed. Important lawsuits here involve the Consumers Power Company (Big Rock Nuclear Plant in Charlevoix, Michigan); attempts by various oil companies and the state of Michigan to allow drilling within the Pigeon River State Forest; and the banning of the pesticide DDT.
  The Michigan Environmental Protection Foundation's legal actions are concerned with specific lawsuits where it hoped to establish legal precedents on issues of environmental quality and protection. The records concern in part the development of property on Little Traverse Bay and Torch Lake; advertising on Grand Rapids city benches; the proper uses of nuclear power; and highway construction.
  - Attorney's Fees No. 3137, No. 23011, No. 57274 (Box 14)
  - Betz Foundry v. WMEAC et. al. No. 11409 No. 14355 (Box 14)
  - Big Rock Nuclear Power Plant; Charlevoix, Michigan
    - No. G58-73CA7
      - Correspondence, notes (Box 14)
      - WMEAC v. AEC March 1973 (Box 14)
      - WMEAC v. AEC April-September 1973 (Box 15)
      - WMEAC v. AEC October-December 1973 (Box 15)
      - WMEAC v. AEC 1974-1975 (Box 15)
    - No. 50-155
      - Correspondence, notes
        - 1971-June 1973 (Box 15)
        - July-December 1973 (Box 15)
        - January-August 1973 (Box 15)
        - September 1973-1975 (Box 15)
      - WMEAC v. ABC March-May 1973 (Box 15)
      - WMEAC v. AEC June-December 1973 (Box 15)
      - WMEAC v. AEC January-July 1974 (Box 15)
      - WMEAC v. AEC August-December 1974 (Box 15)
      - WMEAC V. AEC 1975-1976 (Box 15)
  - Consumers Power Rate Increase
    - Intervention 1973 (Box 15)
    - Shareholder's Proposal 1971-1973 (Box 15)
  - Donald C. Cook Nuclear Plant No. 50-315ED; No. 50-316ED (Box 15)
  - DDT
    - Correspondence, notes
      - 1969-1970 (Box 15)
      - 1971-1974 (Box 16)
    - No. 23,813 court papers
      - 1969 (Box 16)
      - 1970 (Box 16)
      - 1971-1974 (Box 16)
    - No. 71-1256 court papers 1971 (Box 16)
  - Genetic Environmental Statement RM50-5 1976 (Box 16)
  - Goemaere-Anderson Wetland Protection Act (Box 16)
  - Hillsdale County Citizens v. Hillsdale County (Box 16)
  - Hooker Chemical No. 79-22878 CE (Box 16)
  - Kent County-Plainfield Township (Box 16)
  - Lake Dosier Development Co. vs. WMEAC No. 78-0339-AV (Box 16)
  - Nordhouse Dunes
    - Correspondence
      - 1982-1983 (Box 16)
      - 1985 (Box 16)
      - 1986 (Box 16)
      - 1994-1996 (Box 16)
    - Environmental Impact Statement (Draft) (Box 16)
    - Environmental Study (Box 16)
    - Environmental Study Supplement (Box 16)
    - Court Documents December 1995, 3 folders (Box 16)
  - Pigeon River
    - WMEAC et. al. v. NRC et. al. 1976 (Box 16)
    - WMEAC et. al. v. NRC et. al. 1977-1980 No. 76-19335Ce; No. 77-4777 No. 65805, 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Shell Oil v. Tanner 1979-1980 No. 80-24466-AA (Box 17)
    - WMEAC v. Tanner 1980 No. 80-24630-CE; MO. 50236 No. 64786 (Box 17)
    - WMEAC v. NRC et. al. 1980-1981 No. 76-19335 No. 50752 (Box 17)
  - Plutonium Use No. 75-4276 No. 75-4278 (Box 17)
  - Radiation Protection Standard PRM 20-5 (Box 17)
  - Ray v. Mason Co. Drain Commissioner No. 55248 (Box 17)
  - Roberts v. State of Michigan No. 13640 (Box 17)
  - Roadside Obstacles; G76-70 CA 1; WMEAC v. Coleman (Box 17)
  - Zoning; Turkish v. City of Warren (Box 17)
  - Michigan Environmental Protection Foundation
    - Advertising Benches-City of Grand Rapids (Box 17)
    - Consumers Power (Box 17)
    - Consumers Power Advertising (Box 17)
    - Consumers Power Correspondence (Box 17)
    - Grand Haven Canals (Box 17)
    - Kennedy Fund (Box 17)
    - Lake Macatawa (Box 17)
    - Little Traverse Fund (Box 17)
    - MEPF v. Antrim Co. Road Commission-Cedar River (Box 17)
    - Monroe Creek-Lake Charlevoix (Box 17)
    - Organizational Information (Box 17)
    - Pigeon River Drilling Permits (Box 17)
    - Property Development v. Irish et. al (Box 17)
    - Proposed Law Suite (Box 17)
    - Tanton v. DNR (Box 17)
    - Taxpayers etc. v. Highway Dept. of Michigan (Box 17)
    - Torch Lake Case (Box 17)
    - WMEAC v. Reenders (Box 17)
- Chlordane Ban Efforts 1981-1988
  The Chlordane Ban Efforts, 1981-1988 series documents the long struggle of WMEAC and individuals from the local community to support the enactment of a statewide ban on the use of the pesticide Chlordane (a termiticide used extensively by Michigan pest control companies). The series is composed of three parts: Chlordane Investigation (Michigan Dept. of Health), 1985-1986; Newberry, Robert E., (WMEAC Program Specialist and Executive Director) and; Tvedten Steve (Stroz, Inc.).
  Taken together these files illustrate how a typical WMEAC environmental campaign was organized and implemented, and elucidate the various dynamics involved in the interaction of the group with private individuals and businesses and local/state government. The correspondence of Steve Tvedten, president of a Grand Rapids pest control company who became concerned with the health effects of the chemical on his workers and homeowners, in conjunction with the correspondence of Robert Newberry of the WMEAC staff, exemplifies how an individual's concerns were translated into effective political action by WMEAC. The materials on the Chlordane Investigation by the Michigan Dept. of Health (1985-1986) document how WMEAC was able to counteract and question the validity of a government-sponsored investigation which claimed that Chlordane was safe to use. The culmination of the efforts documented in these records was the signing of a state law banning the use of this dangerous pesticide by Governor Blanchard in 1988.
  - Chlordane Investigation (Michigan Dept. of Health) 1985-1986 (Box 18)
  - Newberry, Robert E. (WMEAC Program Specialist and Executive Director) correspondence 1985-1987 (Box 18)
  - Tvedten, Steve (Stroz, Inc.) correspondence 1981-1985, 8 folders (Box 18)
- WMEAC Non-serial Publications
  The WMEAC Non-serial Publications series is comprised of some of the printed materials published by WMEAC, along with some related correspondence/records. The series is divided into Educational Materials and Michigan Environs.
  The Educational Materials contain evidence of the wide-ranging educational efforts undertaken by WMEAC, a topic somewhat under-documented in the rest of the 1994 accession. It is composed primarily of pamphlets, brochures and instructional notebooks produced during the late 1980s and early 1990s. The materials are focused upon four major topical areas: global warming, solid waste disposal, water pollution and youth involvement. Particularly valuable are: the "Global Warming Review," an informative brochure published by WMEAC in 1990 to educate the public on the issues involved; an instructional notebook designed for participants in WMEAC's ambitious "Adopt-A-Stream" program, which outlines the purpose and goals of the program along with information on water pollution reversal tactics and methods; and brochures and pamphlets produced by "YIKES" (Young Idealistic Kids with Environmental Sensitivity), which provide details on the program's goals, activities and accomplishments from 1989 to 1994.
  Michigan Environs is composed of materials relating to WMEAC's attempt during the early 1980s to publish an environmental magazine which was intended to be distributed through individual subscriptions and sales to state public and school libraries. This project was originally grant-funded and expected to become self-sustaining, however, financial and staff limitations led to its demise in 1982.
  - Educational Materials
    - Introductory Packet (Box 18)
    - Global Warming
      - "Global Warming Review" 1990 (Box 18)
    - Solid Waste Disposal
      - "Integrated Waste Management" (Box 18)
    - Water Pollution
      - "Adopt-a-Stream" Program (Box 18)
      - Homeowner's Guides (Box 18)
      - Nonpoint Contamination (Box 18)
      - "Save Your Stream: Manage Your Stormwater" Program (Box 18)
      - Watershed Management (Box 18)
    - Youth Involvement
      - "YIKES" (Young Idealistic Kids with Environmental Sensitivity) (Box 18)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 18)
  - Michigan Environs
    - Editor's Reference Materials
      - Marketing Planning Process (Box 18)
      - Fundraising (Box 18)
      - Editorial, Production and Circulation Information (Box 18)
    - Meadows, Deb (editor)
      - Correspondence 1981 (Box 18)
      - Correspondence 1982-1983 (Box 18)
- WMEAC Publicity and Media Coverage
  The WMEAC Publicity and Media Coverage series documents both internal and external efforts to publicize and analyze programs, campaigns and accomplishments of WMEAC. The materials span virtually the entire history of the group (1968-2005), and are divided into Clippings, Hearing Statements, Photographs, and Press Releases.
  The Clippings consist of primarily newspaper or magazine articles, accumulated by WMEAC staff, that document the programs, activities, and accomplishments of the group over the years. The overwhelming majority of the clippings originate from the Grand Rapids Press and other local West Michigan newspapers and include, along with normal news coverage, various editorials both favorable and unfavorable of WMEAC policies. As such, these chronologically arranged articles present a fascinating account of the interaction between WMEAC and the local community and document the impact of WMEAC on both state and national environmental debates. Also included are several feature-length articles describing the nature and scope of the organization and the motivations and personalities of WMEAC leaders.
  The Hearing Statements are transcripts of testimony delivered by WMEAC members at various legislative and other hearings from 1968 to 1990. These materials are contained within the Publicity and Media Coverage series because they were utilized by WMEAC in a manner similar to press releases, i.e. they were intended mainly to elucidate and publicize WMEAC positions on various legislative and litigious issues.
  The Press Releases is a fairly complete collection of press releases issued by WMEAC. WMEAC employed their press releases as a means of publicizing organizational activities, announcing new programs or staff appointments, and stating official positions on various legislative and other governmental actions, and legal suits in which WMEAC was directly or indirectly involved. Some of the topics covered in this files are: nuclear power, air pollution/Clean Air Act, the banning of the pesticides DDT and Chlordane, the Michigan Bottle Bill, the Michigan Used Motor Oil Recycling Program, the Great Lakes Oil Drilling Ban, the formation of the Michigan Environmental Council and sand dune protection efforts.
  - Clippings
    - 1968-1987, 5 folders (Box 18)
    - 1988-2005, 7 folders (Box 19)
  - Hearing Statements 1968-1990, 4 folders (Box 19)
  - Photographs
    - Adopt A Stream (Box 19)
  - Press Releases
    - 1969-1976 (Box 19)
    - 1979-1982 (Box 19)
    - 1983-1986 (Box 19)
    - 1987-1990 (Box 19)
    - 1988-2005 (Box 19)
- WMEAC Serial Publications
  The WMEAC Serial Publications series includes all publications that have been published with some sort of regularity throughout the organization's existence. The main publication, currently titled Action Issue, has been in continuous publication since April 1970. The name, though, has changed over the years. The "Action Alerts" are a series of informational flyers produced by WMEAC between 1977-1984, which were designed to call the membership's attention to various environmental issues and to promote direct and immediate action through letter-writing campaigns or other lobbying efforts. Published with less regularity are the MCBWM Newsletters, the Michigan Environs Update, and the Sand Dune Bulletin.
  - Main Publication
    - Environmental Action Council Newsletter (name becomes West Michigan Environmental Action Council April 1970-June 1976) (Box 19)
    - Newsletter 1976-1979 (Box 19)
    - Environs 1979-1982 (Box 19)
    - Action Issue 1982-2005, 5 folders (Box 19)
    - Action Issue 1982-2005, 7 folders (Box 20)
  - Action Alerts 1977-1984 (Box 20)
  - MCBWM Newsletters 1978-1980 (Box 20)
  - Michigan Environs Update (scattered) (Box 20)
  - Sand Dune Bulletin (scattered) (Box 20)